Philippine CHAMBAULT

Hollænderdybet 16, 2300 København, Denmark (French, 36 yrs old, she/her/hers

🛮 (+33) 6 43 85 29 60 | 🔀 philippine.chambault@gmail.com | 🎁 pchambault.github.io/portfolio/ | 🖫 pchambault | 🛅 pchambault | Researchgate

Presentation

I am a marine scientist with a broad interest in animal movement and ocean dynamics. I have expertise in quantitative analyses using diverse data sets (e.g., time series, spatial and environmental data) to examine the movement ecology of marine megafauna species in relation to oceanographic processes and how they drive species distribution and diving behaviour.

Education

DEPE - IPHC - CNRS - University of Strasbourg

PhD in Quantitative Ecology and Oceanography

· Habitat use of the French Guianese sea turtles using satellite tracking and oceanographic data

University of Pierre et Marie Curie (UPMC)

MSc in Physical Oceanography and Marine Environment

· Conservation and modeling of marine ecosystems

Strasbourg - FRANCE

Jun 2014-Jun 2017

Paris - FRANCE

Sep 2011-Jun 2013

Experiences

Greenland Institute of Natural Resources, University of California Santa Cruz

MARIE SKŁODOWSKA-CURIE FELLOW: PHYSIOLOGICAL AND BEHAVIORAL RESPONSES OF ARCTIC WHALES TO CLIMATE CHANGE

• Thermal biology, Movement ecology, Acoustics, Species Distribution Modeling (packages: ncdf4, data.table, ggplot2)

Aquarium La Rochelle

POST-DOCTORAL RESEARCHER: THERMAL ECOLOGY OF STRANDED JUVENILE LOGGERHEAD TURTLES

• Satellite tracking, Habitat use (packages: tidyverse, performance, ncdf4, rWind, cvTools, PresenceAbsence, mqcv)

Greenland Institute of Natural Resources

POST-DOCTORAL RESEARCHER: PROJECTIONS OF CLIMATE CHANGE ON POLAR SPECIES

· Machine learning: classification (Random Forest, KNN), regression (logistic, additive), climate models (CMIP6)

• Packages: caret, CAST, gstat, ncdf4, raster, dplyr, doParallel, foreach

IFREMER - MARBEC Sète - FRANC

POST-DOCTORAL RESEARCHER: HABITAT USE OF JUVENILE GREEN TURTLES IN THE INDIAN OCEAN

• Habitat modeling: logistic models, pseudo-absences, SDMs (packages: adehabitatHR, adehabitatHS, rgdal)

University of the Azores - IMAR

POST-DOCTORAL RESEARCHER: INTERACTIONS BETWEEN MARINE LITTER AND JUVENILE LOGGERHEAD TURTLES

• Spatial modeling: physical oceanography, mixed models, drifter data

Greenland Institute of Natural Resources

POST-DOCTORAL RESEARCHER: HABITAT AFFINITIES OF SATELLITE TRACKED BOWHEAD WHALES

• Habitat modeling: GAMs, GLMs, Copernicus database (packages: mgcv, ncdf4, glmer)

Institut Pluridisciplinaire Hubert Curien - CNRS

 ${\sf PHD}\ {\sf STUDENT}; \ {\sf Influence}\ {\sf of}\ {\sf oceanographic}\ {\sf structures}\ {\sf on}\ {\sf sea}\ {\sf turtles}\ {\sf movements}\ {\sf in}\ {\sf the}\ {\sf North}\ {\sf Atlantic}$

• Habitat use: residence time, state space model, kernel density, diving behaviour

Centre d'Études Biologiques de Chizé - CNRS

RESEARCH ASSISTANT: HABITAT USE OF THE BOTTLENOSE DOLPHIN OF THE NORMAND-BRETON GULF

• Geostatistics & habitat modeling: variogram, kriging, GAMs

USA - DENMARK

Oct 2021-Present

La Rochelle - FRANCE

Jan 2021-Jul 2021

Copenhagen - DENMARK

May 2020-Dec 2020

Sète - FRANCE Nov 2018-Apr 2020

Azores - PORTUGAL

Apr 2018-Oct 2018

Paris - FRANCE

Oct 2017-Apr 2018

Strasbourg - FRANCE

Jun 2014-Jun 2017

Beauvoir-sur-Niort - FRANCE

Feb 2013-Jun 2013

Publications _____

23 ARTICLES, 17 AS 1 st AUTHOR, 2.6 ARTICLES/YEAR, CITATIONS: 571

2024	P. Lelong, [], P. Chambault , et al. Demography of endangered juvenile green turtles in face of environmental changes: 10 years of capture-mark-recapture efforts in Martinique. 291, 110471. (IF: 5.9, cites:	Biol. Conserv.	
2024	0). j.biocon.2024.110471	Biol. Conserv.	
2024	P. Chambault , et al. The nightscape of the Arctic winter shapes the diving behavior of a marine predator. (IF: 4.6, cites: 0). 10.1038/s41598-024-53953-w	Sci. Rep.	
2023	P. Chambault , et al. Extremely low seasonal prey capture efficiency in a deep diving whale, the narwhal. (IF: 3.812, cites: 4). doi.org/10.1098/rsbl.2022.0423	Bio. Lett.	
	Heide-Jørgensent, P. Chambault , et al. A regime shift in the Southeast Greenland marine ecosystem. 29(3).	Glob. Chang. Bio.	
2023	668-685. (IF: 10.863, cites: 12). doi.org/10.1111/gcb.16494 P. Chambault , et al. Future seasonal changes in habitat for Arctic whales during predicted ocean warming.	0:41	
2022	(IF: 14.136, cites: 22). 10.1126/sciadv.abn242		
2021	P. Chambault , et al. Ecological trap or favorable habitat? First evidence that immature sea turtles may survive at their range-limits in the North-East Atlantic. (IF: 4.435, cites: 6). doi.org/10.3389/fmars.2021.736604	Front. Mar. Sci.	
2021	P. Chambault, et al. A methodological framework to predict the individual and population-level distributions from tracking data. 11(3). 1432-1445. (IF: 6.5, cites: 12). doi.org/10.1111/ecog.05436	Ecography	
2021	P. Chambault , et al. Predicting seasonal movements and distribution of the sperm whale using machine learning algorithms. 44(5). 766-777. (IF: 3.17, cites: 25). doi.org/10.1002/ece3.7154	Ecol. Evol.	
2020	P. Chambault , et al. The impact of rising sea temperatures on an Arctic top predator, the narwhal 10(1). 1-10. (IF: 4.996, cites: 35). doi.org/10.1038/s41598-020-75658-6	Sci. Rep.	
2020	F. Siegwalt, [], P. Chambault , et al. High site fidelity of immature green turtles (<i>Chelonia mydas</i>) to their		
2020	foraging grounds revealed by satellite tracking and capture-mark-recapture and consequences for key marine conservation areas. (IF: 5.99, cites: 33). doi.org/10.1016/j.biocon.2020.108742	Biol. Conserv.	
2020	P. Chambault , et al. Contrasted habitats and individual plasticity drive the fine scale movements of juvenile green turtles in coastal ecosystems. 8(1). 1-15. (IF: 3.6, cites: 24). 10.1186/s40462-019-0184-2	Mov. Eco.	
	M. Bonola, [], P. Chambault , et al. Fine scale geographic residence and annual primary production drive	0: 0	
2019	body condition of wild immature green turtles (<i>Chelonia mydas</i>) in Martinique Island (Lesser Antilles). 8(12). (IF: 2.33, cites: 8). 10.1242/bio.048058	Bio. Open	
2019	P. Chambault , et al. Swirling in the ocean: immature loggerhead turtles seasonally target old anticyclonic eddies at the fringe of the North Atlantic gyre. 175. 345-358. (IF: 3.95, cites: 23). 10.1016/j.pocean.2019.05.005	Prog. Oceanogr.	
2018	P. Chambault , et al. Distribution and composition of floating litter off the Azores archipelago and Madeira (NE Atlantic) using opportunistic surveys. 141. 225-232. (IF: 3.13, cites: 34). 10.1016/j.marenvres.2018.09.015	Mar. Environ. Res.	
2018	P. Chambault, et al. Connecting paths between juvenile and adult habitats in the Atlantic green turtle using genetics and satellite tracking. 8(24). 12790-12802. (IF: 3.17, cites: 30). doi.org/10.1002/ece3.4708	Ecol. Evol.	
2018	P. Chambault, et al. Sea surface temperature predicts the movements of an Arctic cetacean: the bowhead whale. 8(1). 9658. (IF: 4.996, cites: 78). 10.1038/s41598-018-27966-1	Sci. Rep.	
	M. Nivière, P. Chambault , et al. Identification of marine key areas across the Caribbean to ensure the		
2018	conservation of the critically endangered hawksbill turtle. 223. 170-180. (IF: 5.99, cites: 31). 10.1016/j.biocon.2018.05.002	Biol. Conserv.	
2017	P. Chambault , et al. The Gulf Stream frontal system: A key oceanographic feature in the habitat selection of the leatherback turtle? 123. 35-47. (IF: 2.955, cites: 27). 10.1016/j.dsr.2017.03.003	Deep. Sea Res. I	
2016	P. Chambault , et al. Habitat use and diving behaviour of gravid olive ridley sea turtles under riverine conditions in French Guiana. 165. 115-123. (IF: 2.96, cites: 8). 10.1016/j.jmarsys.2016.10.005	J. Mar. Syst.	
2016	P. Chambault , et al. Inter-nesting behavioral adjustments of green turtles to an estuarine habitat in French	Mar. Ecol. Prog. Ser.	
2016	P. Chambault, et al. The influence of oceanographic features on the foraging behavior of the olive ridley sea		
	turtle <i>Lepidochelys olivacea</i> along the Guiana coast. 142. 58-71. (IF: 3.95, cites: 48). 10.1016/j.pocean.2016.01.006	Progr. Oceanogr.	
2015	P. Chambault , et al. Dispersal and diving adjustments of the green turtle <i>Chelonia mydas</i> in response to dynamic environmental conditions during post-nesting migration. 10(9). e0137340. (IF: 3.240, cites: 24).	PloS one	
	10.1371/journal.pone.0137340	1 100 0116	
2015	M. Baudouin, B. de Thoisy, P. Chambault , et al. Identification of key marine areas for conservation based on satellite tracking of post-nesting migrating green turtles (<i>Chelonia mydas</i>). 184. 36-41. (IF: 5.99, cites: 59). 10.1016/j.biocon.2014.12.021	Biol. Conserv.	
	10110120/jibi0001120111121021		

Conferences _____

Mar. 2024	P. Chambault, The nightscape of the Arctic winter shapes the diving behavior of a marine predator. $BLS8^{th}$ International Biologging Society.	Poster-JAPAN
Mar. 2022	P. Chambault , Ecological trap or favorable habitat? First evidence that immature sea turtles may survive at their range-limits in the North-East Atlantic. International Sea Turtle Symposium.	Talk-Virtual
Dec. 2021	P. Chambault, Narwhals in a sauna. NAMMCO Working Group on Narwhal in West Greenland (invited speaker).	Talk-CANADA
Oct. 2021	P. Chambault, Arctic whales in warming waters: demographic and behavioural consequences? $BLS7^{th}$ International Biologging Society (invited speaker).	Plenary-Virtual
Dec. 2019	P. Chambault , Sea surface temperature drives narwhals' movements in the Arctic. World Marine Marine Mammal Conference.	Oral-SPAIN
Nov. 2018	P. Chambault , Argos and genetics reveal connecting paths between juvenile and adult habitats in green turtles. Argos conference. Collecte Localisation Satellite.	Oral-FRANCE
Oct. 2016	P. Chambault , Distribution and diving behavior of the French Guianese sea turtles satellite tracked via Argos. Argos conference. Collecte Localisation Satellite.	Oral-FRANCE
Mar. 2016	P. Chambault, The influence of oceanographic features on the foraging behavior of the olive ridley sea turtle <i>Lepidochelys olivacea</i> along the Guiana coast. 36 th Annual Sea turtle Symposium.	Oral-PERU
Mar. 2016	P. Chambault, Developmental habitat and migratory pathways: identifying key areas to protect future breeding green turtles across the Caribbean. 36 th Annual Sea turtle Symposium.	Poster-PERU
May. 201	P. Chambault, Dispersal and diving adjustments of green turtles in response to dynamic environmental conditions during post-nesting migration. 11^{th} Ecology & Behaviour meeting.	Oral-FRANCE
Apr. 2015	P. Chambault, Post-nesting migration of green turtles to their foraging grounds: Dispersal and diving adjustments in response to dynamic environmental conditions. 35^{th} Annual Sea turtle Symposium.	Oral-TURKEY
Apr. 2015	P. Chambault, Migration over the Guyana continental shelf: distribution and diving behavior in relation to mesoscale features. 35^{th} Annual Sea turtle Symposium.	Poster-TURKEY

Awards & Honours _____

2021	Marie Sklodowska-Curie grant, Global fellowship of 3 years, €289,000	DENMARK-USA
2018	Young researchers award, Foundation for the Research on Biodiversity (FRB)	FRANCE
2016	Finalist - 1 st place , Regional final of the "3 minutes thesis" (3MT $^{\circ}$)	FRANCE
2016	Finalist - 1st place , Best poster at the 36 th International Sea Turtle Symposium	PERU
2016	Finalist , Travel grant for the 36^{th} International Sea Turtle Symposium	PERU

Skills_____

Programming R, R Markdown, Quarto, LaTeX, ArcGIS

Writing Grant applications, scientific papers (23 published), reporting

Communication Lectures, interviews, plenary at conferences, finalist of the 3 minute thesis contest

Language French (native), English (fluent, TOEFL), Spanish & Portuguese (beginner))

Teaching & Supervising _____

PhD students 2 MSc students 8

Lectures R lessons on data wrangling (2017), R lessons on spatial data (May 2023, UCSC)

Fieldwork Experiences

Aerial survey for abundnace estimates of cetaceans

GINR

GREENLAND Au-Sep 2024

• Species identification and counting of whales and dolphins from a Twin Otter aircraft over Greenland.

Thermal biology of captive whales and dolphins

UCSC & Georgia Aquarium

USA

Apr 2022-Nov 2023

· Tag development, tag assembling, experimental design, data collection from bottlenose dolphins and beluga whales.

Tagging of bowhead whales

GREENLAND May 2022-May 2023

• Bowhead whale tagging from boats in Qeqertarsuaq (West Greenland).

Tagging of harbour porpoises

GREENLAND

• Harbour porpoises capture using nets and tagging in Maniitsoq (Southwest Greenland).

Tagging of juvenile green turtles

DFPF-IPHC

MARTINIQUE Jun. and Oct. 2016

· Turtle capture at-sea, measurements (length, width and body mass), tagging (flipper and satellite tags).

Tagging of adult female sea turtles

DEPE-IPHC

FRENCH GUIANA Jun. 2016

• Nocturnal beach patrols (7h duration), measurements (length, width), eggs counting.

Photo-identification of bottlenose dolphins

Murdoch University

WESTERN AUSTRALIA Apr-Jun. 2012

• Boat surveys, photographs of dorsal fins.

References

PROFESSOR

Philippe Gaspar gaspar.philippe@gmail.com

OCEANOGRAPHER **FRANCE**

• Mercator Ocean International, CLS

Mads Peter Heide-Jørgensen

mhj@ghsdk.dk

DENMARK

• Greenland Institute of Natural Resources, Copenhagen, Denmark

Terrie Williams tmwillia@ucsc.edu

UNITED STATES of AMERICA

• University of Canifornia Santa Cruz, Santa Cruz

Extracurricular Activities

Art Wildlife photography, drawing, painting (alcohol inks)

Water Scuba diving (PADI Advanced Open Water and CMAS level II, 40 dives), snorkelling

Indoor Vinyasa yoga (twice a week), bouldering

Outdoor Skiing (since I am 4 years old!), Horse riding (dressage and jumping for 12 years, 8 years in competition), hiking, travelling